<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="user-advanced">
  <title>Advanced Concepts</title>

  <para>This chapter discusses some of the more advanced concepts of JGroups
  with respect to using it and setting it up correctly.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Using multiple channels</title>

    <para>When using a fully virtual synchronous protocol stack, the
    performance may not be great because of the larger number of protocols
    present. For certain applications, however, throughput is more important
    than ordering, e.g. for video/audio streams or airplane tracking. In the
    latter case, it is important that airplanes are handed over between
    control domains correctly, but if there are a (small) number of radar
    tracking messages (which determine the exact location of the plane)
    missing, it is not a problem. The first type of messages do not occur very
    often (typically a number of messages per hour), whereas the second type
    of messages would be sent at a rate of 10-30 messages/second. The same
    applies for a distributed whiteboard: messages that represent a video or
    audio stream have to be delivered as quick as possible, whereas messages
    that represent figures drawn on the whiteboard, or new participants
    joining the whiteboard have to be delivered according to a certain
    order.</para>

    <para>The requirements for such applications can be solved by using two
    separate stacks: one for control messages such as group membership, floor
    control etc and the other one for data messages such as video/audio
    streams (actually one might consider using one channel for audio and one
    for video). The control channel might use virtual synchrony, which is
    relatively slow, but enforces ordering and retransmission, and the data
    channel might use a simple UDP channel, possibly including a fragmentation
    layer, but no retransmission layer (losing packets is preferred to costly
    retransmission).</para>

    <para>The <classname>Draw2Channels</classname> demo program (in the
    <classname>org.jgroups.demos</classname> package) demonstrates how to use
    two different channels.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Multiplexer to run multiple building blocks over the same
    channel</title>

    <para>In JBoss we have multiple JGroups channels, one for each application
    (e.g. JBossCache, ClusterPartition etc).</para>

    <para>The goal of the Multiplexer is to combine all stacks with the
    <emphasis>same</emphasis> configuration into one, and have multiple
    services on top of that same channel.</para>

    <para>To do this, we have to introduce multiplexing and demultiplexing
    functionality, ie. each service will have to have a unique service ID (a
    string), and when sending a message, the message has to be tagged with
    that ID. When receiving a message, it will be dispatched to the right
    destination service based on the ID attached to the message. We require
    special handling for VIEW and SUSPECT messages: those need to be
    dispatched to *all* services. State transfer also needs to be handled
    specially, here we probably have to use thread locals, or change the API
    (TBD).</para>

    <para>When deployed into JBoss, the Multiplexer will be exposed as an
    MBean, and all services that depend on it will be deployed with dependency
    injection on the Multiplexer. Of course, the old configuration will still
    be supported.</para>

    <para>The config of the Multiplexer is done via a config file, which lists
    a number of stacks, each keyed by a name, e.g. "udp", "tcp", "tcp-nio"
    etc. See ./conf/stacks.xml for an example. An app is configured with the
    name of a stack, e.g. "udp", and a reference to the Multiplexer MBean. It
    will get a proxy channel through which all of its communication will take
    place. The proxy channel (MuxChannel) will mux/demux messages to the real
    JGroups channel.</para>

    <para>The advantage of the Multiplexer is that we can reduce N channels
    into M where M &lt; N. This means fewer threads, therefore fewer context
    switches, less memory consumption and easier configuration and better
    support.</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Multiplexer API</title>

      <para>The Multiplexer is actually a JChannelFactory, which is configured
      with a reference to an XML configuration file, and has a few additional
      methods to get a Channel. The channel returned is actually an instance
      of MuxChannel, which transparently forwards all invocations to the
      underlying JChannel, and performs multiplexing and demultiplexing.
      Multiple MuxChannels can share the same underlying JChannel, and each
      message sent by a service over the MuxChannel will add the services's ID
      to the message (as a header). That ID is then used to demultiplex the
      message to the correct MuxChannel when received.</para>

      <para>The methods of the JChannelFactory are:</para>

      <screen>
                public Channel createMultiplexerChannel(String stack_name, String id) throws Exception;
                public Channel createMultiplexerChannel(String stack_name, String id, boolean register_for_state_transfer, String substate_id) throws Exception;
            </screen>

      <para>The stack_name parameter refers to a channel configuration defined
      in a separate file (see below).</para>

      <para>The id parameter is the service ID and has to be unique for all
      services sitting on the same channel. If an ID is used more than once,
      when trying to call createMultiplexerChannel(), an exception will be
      thrown.</para>

      <para>the register_for_state_transfer and substate_id parameters are
      discussed below (in <xref linkend="MultipleStateTransfers" />).</para>

      <para>The stack_name parameter is a reference to a stack, for example
      defined in stacks.xml. A shortened version of stacks.xml is shown
      below:</para>

      <screen>
                &lt;protocol_stacks&gt;
                    &lt;stack name="fc-fast-minimalthreads" description="Flow control, no up or down threads"&gt;
                        &lt;config&gt;
                            &lt;UDP    mcast_port="45566"
                                    enable_bundling="true"/&gt;
                            ...
                            &lt;pbcast.STATE_TRANSFER down_thread="false" up_thread="false"/&gt;
                        &lt;/config&gt;
                    &lt;/stack&gt;

                    &lt;stack name="sequencer" description="Totally ordered multicast using a sequencer"&gt;
                        &lt;config&gt;
                            // config
                        &lt;/config&gt;
                    &lt;/stack&gt;

                    &lt;stack name="tcp" description="Using TCP as transport"&gt;
                        &lt;config&gt;
                            &lt;TCP start_port="7800" loopback="true" send_buf_size="100000" recv_buf_size="200000"/&gt;
                            &lt;TCPPING timeout="3000" initial_hosts="localhost[7800]" port_range="3" num_initial_members="3"/&gt;
                            &lt;FD timeout="2000" max_tries="4"/&gt;
                            &lt;VERIFY_SUSPECT timeout="1500" down_thread="false" up_thread="false"/&gt;
                            &lt;pbcast.NAKACK gc_lag="100" retransmit_timeout="600,1200,2400,4800"/&gt;
                            &lt;pbcast.STABLE stability_delay="1000" desired_avg_gossip="20000" down_thread="false" max_bytes="0" up_thread="false"/&gt;
                            &lt;VIEW_SYNC avg_send_interval="60000" down_thread="false" up_thread="false" /&gt;
                            &lt;pbcast.GMS print_local_addr="true" join_timeout="5000" shun="true"/&gt;
                        &lt;/config&gt;
                    &lt;/stack&gt;

                    &lt;stack name="discovery" description="Simple UDP-only stack for discovery"&gt;
                        &lt;config&gt;
                            &lt;UDP mcast_port="7609"
                                 mcast_addr="228.15.15.15"
                                 ip_ttl="32"/&gt;
                        &lt;/config&gt;
                    &lt;/stack&gt;
                &lt;/protocol_stacks&gt;
            </screen>

      <para>This file defines 4 configurations: fc-fast-minimalthreads,
      sequencer, tcp and discovery. The first service to call
      JChannelFactory.createMultiplexerChannel() with a stack_name of "tcp"
      will create the JChannel with the "tcp" configuration, all subsequent
      method calls for the <emphasis>same</emphasis> stack_name ("tcp") will
      simply get a MuxChannel which has a reference to the same underlying
      JChannel. When a service closes a MuxChannel, the underlying JChannel
      will only be closed when there are no more MuxChannels referring to
      it.</para>

      <para>For more information on Multiplexing refer to
      JGroups/doc/design/Multiplexer.txt</para>

      <section id="MultipleStateTransfers">
        <title>Batching state transfers</title>

        <para>Note that this feature is currently <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        used in JBoss, because JBoss doesn't call all create() methods of all
        dependent beans first, and then all start() methods. The call sequence
        is indeterministic unless all dependent beans are defined in the same
        XML file, which is unrealistic. We're looking into using a barrier
        service to provide the guarantee that all create() methods are called
        before all start() methods, possibly in JBoss 5.</para>

        <para>When multiple services are sharing a JChannel, and each of the
        services requires state transfer at a different time, then we need
        FLUSH (see ./doc/design/PartialStateTransfer.txt for a description of
        the problem). FLUSH is also called the stop-the-world model, and
        essentially stops everyone in a group from sending messages until the
        state has been transferred, and then everyone can resume again. <note>
             The 2.3 release of JGroups will 

            <emphasis>not</emphasis>

             have the FLUSH protocol integrated, so state transfer for the Multiplexer might be incorrect. 2.4 will have FLUSH, so that situation will be corrected. The main reason for putting Multiplexing into 2.3 is that people can start programming against the API, and then use it when FLUSH is available. 
          </note></para>

        <para>When multiple services share one JChannel, then we have to run
        the FLUSH protocol for every service which requires state, so if we
        have services A, B, C, D and E running on top of a JChannel J, and B,C
        and E require state, then the FLUSH protocol has to be run 3 times,
        which slows down startup (e.g.) of JBoss.</para>

        <para>To remedy this, we can <emphasis>batch</emphasis> state
        transfers, so that we suspend everyone from sending messages, then
        fetch the states for B, C and E at once, and then resume everyone.
        Thus, the FLUSH protocol has to be run only once.</para>

        <para>To do this, a service has to register with the JChannelFactory
        when creating the MuxChannel, and know that getState() will be a no-op
        until the last registered application has called getState(). This
        works as follows: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               B, C and D register for state transfer 
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               B calls MuxChannel.getState(). Nothing happens. 
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               D calls MuxChannel.getState(). Nothing happens. 
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               E calls MuxChannel.getState(). Now everyone who registered has called getState() and therefore we transfer the state for B, C and E (using partial state transfer). 
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               At this point B, C and D's setState() will be called, so that they can set the state. 
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>

        <para>The code below (a snipper from MultiplexerTest) shows how
        services can register for state transfers. In an MBean (JBoss)
        environment, the registration could be done in the create() callback,
        and the actual getState() call in start().</para>

        <screen>
    public void testStateTransferWithRegistration() throws Exception {
        final String STACK_NAME="fc-fast-minimalthreads";
        Channel ch1, ch2;
        ch1=factory.createMultiplexerChannel(STACK_NAME, "c1", true, null); // register for (entire) state transfer
        ch1.connect("bla"); // will create a new JChannel

        ch2=factory.createMultiplexerChannel(STACK_NAME, "c2", true, null); // register for (entire) state transfer
        ch2.connect("bla"); // will share the JChannel created above (same STACK_NAME)

        boolean rc=ch1.getState(null, 5000); // this will *not* trigger the state transfer protocol
        rc=ch2.getState(null, 5000); // only *this* will trigger the state transfer
    }
                </screen>

        <para>The example above shows that 2 services ("c1" and "c2") share a
        common JChannel because they use the same stack_name (STACK_NAME). It
        also shows that only the second getState() invocation will actually
        transfer the 2 states (for "c1" and "c2").</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service views</title>

      <para>When we have multiple service running on the same channel, then
      some services might get redeployed or stopped independently from the other
      services. So we might have a situation where we have services S1, S2 and
      S3 running on host H1, but on host H2, only services S2 and S3 are
      running.</para>

      <para>The <emphasis>cluster view</emphasis> is {H1, H2}, but the
      <emphasis>service views</emphasis> are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
           S1: {H1} 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           S2: {H1, H2} 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           S3: {H1, H2} 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This can also be seen as ordered by hosts:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
           H1: {S1, S2, S3} 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           H2: {S2, S3} 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>So here we host H1 running services S1, S2 and S3, whereas H2 is
      only running S2 and S3. S1 might be in the process of being redeployed
      on H2, or is simply not running.</para>

      <para>A service view is essentially a list of nodes of a cluster on
      which a given service S is currently running. Service views are always
      subsets of cluster views. Here's a reason we need service views:
      consider the example above. Let's say service S1 on H1 wants to make a
      cluster-wide method invocation on all instances of S1 running on any
      host. Now, S1 is only running on H1, therefore we have to make the
      invocation only on S1. However, if we took the cluster view rather than
      the service view, the invocation would be across H1 and H2, and we'd be
      waiting for a response from the (non-existent) service S1 on H2 forever
      !</para>

      <para>So, by default, calling MuxChannel.getView() will return the
      service view rather than the cluster view. The cluster view can be
      retrieved calling MuxChannel.getClusterView().</para>

      <para>There are example unit tests in MultiplexerTest and
      MultiplexerViewTest. The latter tests service views versus cluster
      views.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

    <section>
        <title id="SharedTransport">Sharing a transport between multiple channels in a JVM</title>

        <para>
            To save resources (threads, sockets and CPU cycles), transports of channels residing within the same
            JVM can be shared. If we have 4 channels inside of a JVM (as is the case in an application server
            such as JBoss), then we have 4 separate thread pools and sockets (1 per transport, and there are 4
            transports (1 per channel)).
        </para>

        <para>
            If those transport happen to be the same (all 4 channels use UDP, for example), then we can share them and
            only create 1 instance of UDP. That transport instance is created and started only once, when the first
            channel is created, and is deleted when the last channel is closed.
        </para>

        <para>
            Each channel created over a shared transport has to join a different cluster. An exception will be thrown
            if a channel sharing a transport tries to connect to a cluster to which another channel over the same
            transport is already connected.
        </para>

        <para>
            When we have 3 channels (C1 connected to "cluster-1", C2 connected to "cluster-2" and C3 connected to
            "cluster-3") sending messages over the same shared transport, the cluster name
            with which the channel connected is used to multiplex messages over the shared transport: a header with
            the cluster name ("cluster-1") is added when C1 sends a message.
        </para>

        <para>
            When a message with a header of "cluster-1" is received by the shared transport, it is used to demultiplex
            the message and dispatch it to the right channel (C1 in this example) for processing.
        </para>

        <para>
            How channels can share a single transport is shown in <xref linkend="SharedTransportFig"/>.
        </para>

        <figure id="SharedTransportFig"><title>A shared transport</title>
            <graphic fileref="images/SharedTransport.png" format="PNG" align="center"  />
        </figure>

        <para>
            Here we see 4 channels which share 2 transports. Note that first 3 channels which share transport
            "tp_one" have the same protocols on top of the shared transport. This is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
            required; the protocols above "tp_one" could be different for each of the 3 channels as long
            as all applications residing on the same shared transport have the same requirements for the transport's
            configuration.
        </para>

        <para>
            To use shared transports, all we need to do is to add a property "singleton_name" to the transport
            configuration. All channels with the same singleton name will be shared.
        </para>
    </section>

  <section>
    <title>Transport protocols</title>

    <para>A <emphasis>transport protocol</emphasis> refers to the protocol at
    the bottom of the protocol stack which is responsible for sending and
    receiving messages to/from the network. There are a number of transport
    protocols in JGroups. They are discussed in the following sections.</para>

    <para>A typical protocol stack configuration using UDP is:</para>

      <screen>
                    &lt;config&gt;
                        &lt;UDP
                             mcast_addr="${jgroups.udp.mcast_addr:228.10.10.10}"
                             mcast_port="${jgroups.udp.mcast_port:45588}"
                             discard_incompatible_packets="true"
                             max_bundle_size="60000"
                             max_bundle_timeout="30"
                             ip_ttl="${jgroups.udp.ip_ttl:2}"
                             enable_bundling="true"
                             thread_pool.enabled="true"
                             thread_pool.min_threads="1"
                             thread_pool.max_threads="25"
                             thread_pool.keep_alive_time="5000"
                             thread_pool.queue_enabled="false"
                             thread_pool.queue_max_size="100"
                             thread_pool.rejection_policy="Run"
                             oob_thread_pool.enabled="true"
                             oob_thread_pool.min_threads="1"
                             oob_thread_pool.max_threads="8"
                             oob_thread_pool.keep_alive_time="5000"
                             oob_thread_pool.queue_enabled="false"
                             oob_thread_pool.queue_max_size="100"
                             oob_thread_pool.rejection_policy="Run"/&gt;
                        &lt;PING timeout="2000"
                                num_initial_members="3"/&gt;
                        &lt;MERGE2 max_interval="30000"
                                min_interval="10000"/&gt;
                        &lt;FD_SOCK/&gt;
                        &lt;FD timeout="10000" max_tries="5"   shun="true"/&gt;
                        &lt;VERIFY_SUSPECT timeout="1500"  /&gt;
                        &lt;pbcast.NAKACK
                                       use_mcast_xmit="false" gc_lag="0"
                                       retransmit_timeout="300,600,1200,2400,4800"
                                       discard_delivered_msgs="true"/&gt;
                        &lt;UNICAST timeout="300,600,1200,2400,3600"/&gt;
                        &lt;pbcast.STABLE stability_delay="1000" desired_avg_gossip="50000"
                                       max_bytes="400000"/&gt;
                        &lt;pbcast.GMS print_local_addr="true" join_timeout="3000"
                                    shun="false"
                                    view_bundling="true"/&gt;
                        &lt;FC max_credits="20000000"
                                        min_threshold="0.10"/&gt;
                        &lt;FRAG2 frag_size="60000"  /&gt;
                        &lt;pbcast.STATE_TRANSFER  /&gt;
                    &lt;/config&gt;
                </screen>
    

    <para>In a nutshell the properties of the protocols are:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>UDP</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This is the transport protocol. It uses IP multicasting to send messages to the entire cluster, or
          individual nodes. Other transports include TCP, TCP_NIO and TUNNEL.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>PING</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Uses IP multicast (by default) to find initial members. Once
          found, the current coordinator can be determined and a unicast JOIN
          request will be sent to it in order to join the cluster.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>MERGE2</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Will merge subgroups back into one group, kicks in after a cluster partition.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>FD_SOCK</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Failure detection based on sockets (in a ring form between
          members). Generates notification if a member fails</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term>FD</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Failure detection based on heartbeats and are-you-alive messages (in a ring form between
          members). Generates notification if a member fails</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>VERIFY_SUSPECT</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Double-checks whether a suspected member is really dead,
          otherwise the suspicion generated from protocol below is discarded</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>pbcast.NAKACK</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ensures (a) message reliability and (b) FIFO. Message
          reliability guarantees that a message will be received. If not,
          the receiver(s) will request retransmission. FIFO guarantees that all
          messages from sender P will be received in the order P sent them</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>UNICAST</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Same as NAKACK for unicast messages: messages from sender P
          will not be lost (retransmission if necessary) and will be in FIFO
          order (conceptually the same as TCP in TCP/IP)</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

           <varlistentry>
        <term>pbcast.STABLE</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Deletes messages that have been seen by all members (distributed message garbage collection)</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
            <term>pbcast.GMS</term>

            <listitem>
                <para>Membership protocol. Responsible for joining/leaving members and installing new views.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>FRAG2</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Fragments large messages into smaller ones and reassembles
          them back at the receiver side. For both multicast and unicast messages</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
        <term>STATE_TRANSFER</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>
              Ensures that state is correctly transferred from an existing member (usually the coordinator) to a
              new member.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>


    </variablelist>

    <section>
      <title>UDP</title>

      <para>UDP uses IP multicast for sending messages to all members of a
      group and UDP datagrams for unicast messages (sent to a single member).
      When started, it opens a unicast and multicast socket: the unicast
      socket is used to send/receive unicast messages, whereas the multicast
      socket sends/receives multicast messages. The channel's address will be
      the address and port number of the <emphasis>unicast</emphasis>
      socket.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Using UDP and plain IP multicasting</title>

        <para>A protocol stack with UDP as transport protocol is typically
        used with groups whose members run on the same host or are distributed
        across a LAN. Before running such a stack a programmer has to ensure
        that IP multicast is enabled across subnets. It is often the case that
        IP multicast is not enabled across subnets. Refer to section <xref
        linkend="ItDoesntWork" /> for running a test program that determines
        whether members can reach each other via IP multicast. If this does
        not work, the protocol stack cannot use UDP with IP multicast as
        transport. In this case, the stack has to either use UDP without IP
        multicasting or other transports such as TCP.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="IpNoMulticast">
        <title>Using UDP without IP multicasting</title>

        <para>The protocol stack with UDP and PING as the bottom protocols use
        IP multicasting by default to send messages to all members (UDP) and
        for discovery of the initial members (PING). However, if multicasting
        cannot be used, the UDP and PING protocols can be configured to send
        multiple unicast messages instead of one multicast message <footnote>
            <para>Although not as efficient (and using more bandwidth), it is
            sometimes the only possibility to reach group members.</para>
          </footnote> (UDP) and to access a well-known server (
        <emphasis>GossipRouter</emphasis> ) for initial membership information
        (PING).</para>

        <para>To configure UDP to use multiple unicast messages to send a
        group message instead of using IP multicasting, the
        <parameter>ip_mcast</parameter> property has to be set to
        <literal>false</literal> .</para>

        <para>To configure PING to access a GossipRouter instead of using IP
        multicast the following properties have to be set:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>gossip_host</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The name of the host on which GossipRouter is
              started</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>gossip_port</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The port on which GossipRouter is listening</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>gossip_refresh</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The number of milliseconds to wait until refreshing our
              address entry with the GossipRouter</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>Before any members are started the GossipRouter has to be
        started, e.g.</para>

          <screen>
              java org.jgroups.stack.GossipRouter -port 5555 -bindaddress localhost
          </screen>

        <para>This starts the GossipRouter on the local host on port 5555. The
        GossipRouter is essentially a lookup service for groups and members.
        It is a process that runs on a well-known host and port and accepts
        GET(group) and REGISTER(group, member) requests. The REGISTER request
        registers a member's address and group with the GossipRouter. The GET
        request retrieves all member addresses given a group name. Each member
        has to periodically ( <parameter>gossip_refresh</parameter> )
        re-register their address with the GossipRouter, otherwise the entry
        for that member will be removed (accommodating for crashed
        members).</para>

        <para>The following example shows how to disable the use of IP
        multicasting and use a GossipRouter instead. Only the bottom two
        protocols are shown, the rest of the stack is the same as in the
        previous example:</para>

        <screen>
                    &lt;UDP ip_mcast="false" mcast_addr="224.0.0.35" mcast_port="45566" ip_ttl="32"
                         mcast_send_buf_size="150000" mcast_recv_buf_size="80000"/&gt;
                    &lt;PING gossip_host="localhost" gossip_port="5555" gossip_refresh="15000"
                          timeout="2000" num_initial_members="3"/&gt;
                </screen>

        <para>The property <parameter>ip_mcast</parameter> is set to
        <literal>false</literal> in <classname>UDP</classname> and the gossip
        properties in <classname>PING</classname> define the GossipRouter to
        be on the local host at port 5555 with a refresh rate of 15 seconds.
        If PING is parameterized with the GossipRouter's address
        <emphasis>and</emphasis> port, then gossiping is enabled, otherwise it
        is disabled. If only one parameter is given, gossiping will be
        <emphasis>disabled</emphasis> .</para>

        <para>Make sure to run the GossipRouter before starting any members,
        otherwise the members will not find each other and each member will
        form its own group <footnote>
            <para>This can actually be used to test the MERGE2 protocol: start
            two members (forming two singleton groups because they don't find
            each other), then start the GossipRouter. After some time, the two
            members will merge into one group</para>
          </footnote> .</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>TCP</title>

      <para>TCP is a replacement of UDP as bottom layer in cases where IP
      Multicast based on UDP is not desired. This may be the case when
      operating over a WAN, where routers will discard IP MCAST. As a rule of
      thumb UDP is used as transport for LANs, whereas TCP is used for
      WANs.</para>

      <para>The properties for a typical stack based on TCP might look like
      this (edited/protocols removed for brevity):</para>

      <screen>
    &lt;TCP start_port="7800" /&gt;
    &lt;TCPPING timeout="3000"
             initial_hosts="${jgroups.tcpping.initial_hosts:localhost[7800],localhost[7801]}"
             port_range="1"
             num_initial_members="3"/&gt;
    &lt;VERIFY_SUSPECT timeout="1500"  /&gt;
    &lt;pbcast.NAKACK
                   use_mcast_xmit="false" gc_lag="0"
                   retransmit_timeout="300,600,1200,2400,4800"
                   discard_delivered_msgs="true"/&gt;
    &lt;pbcast.STABLE stability_delay="1000" desired_avg_gossip="50000"
                   max_bytes="400000"/&gt;
    &lt;pbcast.GMS print_local_addr="true" join_timeout="3000"
                shun="true"
                view_bundling="true"/&gt;
            </screen>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>TCP</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The transport protocol, uses TCP (from TCP/IP) to send
            unicast and multicast messages. In the latter case, it sends
            multiple unicast messages.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>TCPPING</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Discovers the initial membership to determine coordinator.
            Join request will then be sent to coordinator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VERIFY_SUSPECT</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Double checks that a suspected member is really dead</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>pbcast.NAKACK</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Reliable and FIFO message delivery</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
          <term>pbcast.STABLE</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Distributed garbage collection of messages seen by all
            members</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>pbcast.GMS</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Membership services. Takes care of joining and removing
            new/old members, emits view changes</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Since TCP already offers some of the reliability guarantees that
      UDP doesn't, some protocols (e.g. FRAG and UNICAST) are not needed on
      top of TCP.</para>

      <para>When using TCP, each message to the group is sent as multiple
      unicast messages (one to each member). Due to the fact that IP
      multicasting cannot be used to discover the initial members, another
      mechanism has to be used to find the initial membership. There are a
      number of alternatives:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>PING with GossipRouter: same solution as described in <xref
          linkend="IpNoMulticast" /> . The <parameter>ip_mcast</parameter>
          property has to be set to <literal>false</literal> . GossipRouter
          has to be started before the first member is started.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>TCPPING: uses a list of well-known group members that it
          solicits for initial membership</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>TCPGOSSIP: essentially the same as the above PING <footnote>
              <para>PING and TCPGOSSIP will be merged in the future.</para>
            </footnote> . The only difference is that TCPGOSSIP allows for
          multiple GossipRouters instead of only one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The next two section illustrate the use of TCP with both TCPPING
      and TCPGOSSIP.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Using TCP and TCPPING</title>

        <para>A protocol stack using TCP and TCPPING looks like this (other
        protocols omitted):</para>

        <screen>
                    &lt;TCP start_port="7800" /&gt; +
                    &lt;TCPPING initial_hosts="HostA[7800],HostB[7800]" port_range="5"
                             timeout="3000" num_initial_members="3" /&gt;
                </screen>

        <para>The concept behind TCPPING is that no external daemon such as
        GossipRouter is needed. Instead some selected group members assume the
        role of well-known hosts from which initial membership information can
        be retrieved. In the example <parameter>HostA</parameter> and
        <parameter>HostB</parameter> are designated members that will be used
        by TCPPING to lookup the initial membership. The property
        <parameter>start_port</parameter> in <classname>TCP</classname> means
        that each member should try to assign port 7800 for itself. If this is
        not possible it will try the next higher port (
        <literal>7801</literal> ) and so on, until it finds an unused
        port.</para>

        <para><classname>TCPPING</classname> will try to contact both
        <parameter>HostA</parameter> and <parameter>HostB</parameter> ,
        starting at port <literal>7800</literal> and ending at port
        <literal>7800 + port_range</literal> , in the above example ports
        <literal>7800</literal> - <literal>7804</literal> . Assuming that at
        least one of <parameter>HostA</parameter> or
        <parameter>HostB</parameter> is up, a response will be received. To be
        absolutely sure to receive a response all the hosts on which members
        of the group will be running can be added to the configuration
        string.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using TCP and TCPGOSSIP</title>

        <para>As mentioned before <classname>TCPGOSSIP</classname> is
        essentially the same as <classname>PING</classname> with properties
        <parameter>gossip_host</parameter> ,
        <parameter>gossip_port</parameter> and
        <parameter>gossip_refresh</parameter> set. However, in TCPGOSSIP these
        properties are called differently as shown below (only the bottom two
        protocols are shown):</para>

        <screen>
                    &lt;TCP /&gt;
                    &lt;TCPGOSSIP initial_hosts="localhost[5555],localhost[5556]" gossip_refresh_rate="10000"
                               num_initial_members="3" /&gt;
                </screen>

        <para>The <parameter>initial_hosts</parameter> properties combines
        both the host and port of a GossipRouter, and it is possible to
        specify more than one GossipRouter. In the example there are two
        GossipRouters at ports <literal>5555</literal> and
        <literal>5556</literal> on the local host. Also,
        <parameter>gossip_refresh_rate</parameter> defines how many
        milliseconds to wait between refreshing the entry with the
        GossipRouters.</para>

        <para>The advantage of having multiple GossipRouters is that, as long
        as at least one is running, new members will always be able to
        retrieve the initial membership. Note that the GossipRouter should be
        started before any of the members.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>TUNNEL</title>

      <section>
        <title>Using TUNNEL to tunnel a firewall</title>

        <para>Firewalls are usually placed at the connection to the internet.
        They shield local networks from outside attacks by screening incoming
        traffic and rejecting connection attempts to host inside the firewalls
        by outside machines. Most firewall systems allow hosts inside the
        firewall to connect to hosts outside it (outgoing traffic), however,
        incoming traffic is most often disabled entirely.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Tunnels</emphasis> are host protocols which
        encapsulate other protocols by multiplexing them at one end and
        demultiplexing them at the other end. Any protocol can be tunneled by
        a tunnel protocol.</para>

        <para>The most restrictive setups of firewalls usually disable
        <emphasis>all</emphasis> incoming traffic, and only enable a few
        selected ports for outgoing traffic. In the solution below, it is
        assumed that one TCP port is enabled for outgoing connections to the GossipRouter.</para>

        <para>JGroups has a mechanism that allows a programmer to tunnel a
        firewall. The solution involves a GossipRouter, which has to be outside of the firewall,
        so other members (possibly also behind firewalls) can access it.</para>

        <para>The solution works as follows. A channel inside a firewall has
        to use protocol TUNNEL instead of UDP or TCP as bottommost layer. Recommended 
        discovery protocol is PING, starting with 2.8 release, you do not have to specify 
        any gossip routers in PING. </para>

        <screen>
                    &lt;TUNNEL gossip_router_hosts="127.0.0.1[12001]" /&gt;
                    &lt;PING /&gt;
                </screen>

        <para><classname>TCPGOSSIP</classname> uses the GossipRouter (outside
        the firewall) at port <literal>12001</literal> to register its address
        (periodically) and to retrieve the initial membership for its
        group. It is not recommended to use TCPGOSSIP for discovery if TUNNEL is 
        already used. TCPGOSSIP might be used in rare scenarios when registration and 
        initial member discovery <emphasis>has to be done </emphasis>through gossip 
        router indepedent of transport protocol being used. Starting with 2.8 release 
        TCPGOSSIP accepts one or multiple router hosts as a comma delimited list 
        of host[port] elements specified in a property initial_hosts.</para>

        <para><classname>TUNNEL</classname> establishes a TCP connection to the
        <emphasis>GossipRouter</emphasis> process (also outside the firewall) that
        accepts messages from members and passes them on to other members.
        This connection is initiated by the host inside the firewall and
        persists as long as the channel is connected to a group. GossipRouter will
        use the <emphasis>same connection</emphasis> to send incoming messages
        to the channel that initiated the connection. This is perfectly legal,
        as TCP connections are fully duplex. Note that, if GossipRouter tried to
        establish its own TCP connection to the channel behind the firewall,
        it would fail. But it is okay to reuse the existing TCP connection,
        established by the channel.</para>

        <para>Note that <classname>TUNNEL</classname> has to be given the
        hostname and port of the GossipRouter process. This example assumes a GossipRouter
        is running on the local host at port <literal>12001</literal>. Both
        TUNNEL and TCPGOSSIP (or PING) access the same GossipRouter. 
        Starting with 2.8 release TUNNEL transport layer accepts one or multiple router 
        hosts as a comma delimited list of host[port] elements specified in a 
        property gossip_router_hosts.</para>

        <para>Any time a message has to be sent, TUNNEL forwards the message
        to GossipRouter, which distributes it to its destination: if the message's
        destination field is null (send to all group members), then GossipRouter
        looks up the members that belong to that group and forwards the
        message to all of them via the TCP connection they established when
        connecting to GossipRouter. If the destination is a valid member address,
        then that member's TCP connection is looked up, and the message is
        forwarded to it <footnote>
            <para>To do so, GossipRouter has to maintain a table between groups,
            member addresses and TCP connections.</para>
          </footnote> .</para>
         
         <para> 
          Starting with 2.8 release, gossip router is no longer a single 
		  point of failure. In a set-up with multiple gossip routers, routers do 
		  not communicate among themselves, and single point of failure is avoided 
		  by having each channel simply connect to multiple available routers. In 
          case one or more routers go down, cluster members are still able to 
          exchange message through remaining available router instances, if there 
          are any.

          For each send invocation, a channel goes through a list of available 
          connections to routers and attempts to send a message on each connection 
          until it succeeds. If a message could not be sent on any of the 
          connections – an exception is raised. Default policy for connection 
          selection is random. However, we also provide an plug-in interface for 
          other policies as well.

          Gossip router configuration is static and is not updated for the 
          lifetime of the channel. A list of available routers has to be provided 
          in channel configuration file.</para>

          

        <para>To tunnel a firewall using JGroups, the following steps have to
        be taken:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Check that a TCP port (e.g. 12001) is enabled in
            the firewall for outgoing traffic</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Start the GossipRouter:</para>

            <screen>
                            start org.jgroups.stack.GossipRouter -port 12001
                        </screen>
          </listitem>


          <listitem>
            <para>Configure the TUNNEL protocol layer as instructed
            above.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create a channel</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The general setup is shown in <xref linkend="TunnelingFig" />
        .</para>

        <figure id="TunnelingFig">
          <title>Tunneling a firewall</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/Tunneling.png" />
            </imageobject>

            <textobject>
              <phrase>A diagram representing tunneling a firewall.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>First, the GossipRouter process is created on host
        B. Note that host B should be outside the firewall, and all channels in
        the same group should use the same GossipRouter process.
        When a channel on host A is created, its
        <classname>TCPGOSSIP</classname> protocol will register its address
        with the GossipRouter and retrieve the initial membership (assume this
        is C). Now, a TCP connection with the GossipRouter is established by A; this
        will persist until A crashes or voluntarily leaves the group. When A
        multicasts a message to the group, GossipRouter looks up all group members
        (in this case, A and C) and forwards the message to all members, using
        their TCP connections. In the example, A would receive its own copy of
        the multicast message it sent, and another copy would be sent to
        C.</para>

        <para>This scheme allows for example <emphasis>Java applets</emphasis>
        , which are only allowed to connect back to the host from which they
        were downloaded, to use JGroups: the HTTP server would be located on
        host B and the gossip and GossipRouter daemon would also run on that host.
        An applet downloaded to either A or C would be allowed to make a TCP
        connection to B. Also, applications behind a firewall would be able to
        talk to each other, joining a group.</para>

        <para>However, there are several drawbacks: first, having to maintain a TCP connection for the
        duration of the connection might use up resources in the host system
        (e.g. in the GossipRouter), leading to scalability problems, second, this
        scheme is inappropriate when only a few channels are located behind
        firewalls, and the vast majority can indeed use IP multicast to
        communicate, and finally, it is not always possible to enable outgoing
        traffic on 2 ports in a firewall, e.g. when a user does not 'own' the
        firewall.</para>
        
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>


    <section>
        <title>The concurrent stack</title>

        <para>
            The concurrent stack (introduced in 2.5) provides a number of improvements over previous releases,
            which has some deficiencies:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    Large number of threads: each protocol had by default 2 threads, one for the up and one for the
                    down queue. They could be disabled per protocol by setting up_thread or down_thread to false.
                    In the new model, these threads have been removed.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Sequential delivery of messages: JGroups used to have a single queue for incoming messages,
                    processed by one thread. Therefore, messages from different senders were still processed in
                    FIFO order. In 2.5 these messages can be processed in parallel.
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    Out-of-band messages: when an application doesn't care about the ordering properties of a message,
                    the OOB flag can be set and JGroups will deliver this particular message without regard for any
                    ordering.
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>

            <para>
                The architecture of the concurrent stack is shown in <xref linkend="ConcurrentStackFig"/>. The changes
                were made entirely inside of the transport protocol (TP, with subclasses UDP, TCP and TCP_NIO). Therefore,
                to configure the concurrent stack, the user has to modify the config for (e.g.) UDP in the XML file.
            </para>

            <para>
                <figure id="ConcurrentStackFig"><title>The concurrent stack</title>
                    <graphic fileref="images/ConcurrentStack.png" format="PNG" align="left" />
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>
                
            </para>

            <para>
                The concurrent stack consists of 2 thread pools (java.util.concurrent.Executor): the out-of-band (OOB)
                thread pool and the regular thread pool. Packets are received by multicast or unicast receiver threads
                (UDP) or a ConnectionTable (TCP, TCP_NIO). Packets marked as OOB (with Message.setFlag(Message.OOB)) are
                dispatched to the OOB thread pool, and all other packets are dispatched to the regular thread pool.
            </para>

            <para>
                When a thread pool is disabled, then we use the thread of the caller (e.g. multicast or unicast
                receiver threads or the ConnectionTable) to send the message up the stack and into the application.
                Otherwise, the packet will be processed by a thread from the thread pool, which sends the message up
                the stack. When all current threads are busy, another thread might be created, up to the maximum number
                of threads defined. Alternatively, the packet might get queued up until a thread becomes available.
            </para>

            <para>
                The point of using a thread pool is that the receiver threads should only receive the packets and forward
                them to the thread pools for processing, because unmarshalling and processing is slower than simply
                receiving the message and can benefit from parallelization.
            </para>


            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>

                <para>Note that this is preliminary and names or properties might change</para>

                <para>
                    We are thinking of exposing the thread pools programmatically, meaning that a developer might be able to set both
                    threads pools programmatically, e.g. using something like TP.setOOBThreadPool(Executor executor).
                </para>

                <para>
                    Here's an example of the new configuration:
                    <screen>
                        <![CDATA[
                        <UDP
                                mcast_addr="228.10.10.10"
                                mcast_port="45588"

                                thread_pool.enabled="true"
                                thread_pool.min_threads="1"
                                thread_pool.max_threads="100"
                                thread_pool.keep_alive_time="20000"
                                thread_pool.queue_enabled="false"
                                thread_pool.queue_max_size="10"
                                thread_pool.rejection_policy="Run"

                                oob_thread_pool.enabled="true"
                                oob_thread_pool.min_threads="1"
                                oob_thread_pool.max_threads="4"
                                oob_thread_pool.keep_alive_time="30000"
                                oob_thread_pool.queue_enabled="true"
                                oob_thread_pool.queue_max_size="10"
                                oob_thread_pool.rejection_policy="Run"/>
                                ]]>
                    </screen>
                </para>

                <para>
                    The attributes for the 2 thread pools are prefixed with thread_pool and oob_thread_pool respectively.
                </para>

                <para>
                    The attributes are listed below. The roughly correspond to the options of a
                    java.util.concurrent.ThreadPoolExecutor in JDK 5.
                    <table>
                        <title>Attributes of thread pools</title>

                        <tgroup cols="2">
                            <colspec align="left" />

                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry align="center">Name</entry>
                                    <entry align="center">Description</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>

                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>enabled</entry>
                                    <entry>Whether of not to use a thread pool. If set to false, the caller's thread
                                    is used.</entry>
                                </row>

                                <row>
                                    <entry>min_threads</entry>
                                    <entry>The minimum number of threads to use.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>max_threads</entry>
                                    <entry>The maximum number of threads to use.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>keep_alive_time</entry>
                                    <entry>Number of milliseconds until an idle thread is removed from the pool</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>queue_enabled</entry>
                                    <entry>Whether of not to use a (bounded) queue. If enabled, when all minimum
                                    threads are busy, work items are added to the queue. When the queue is full,
                                    additional threads are created, up to max_threads. When max_threads have been
                                    reached, the rejection policy is consulted.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>max_size</entry>
                                    <entry>The maximum number of elements in the queue. Ignored if the queue is
                                    disabled</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>rejection_policy</entry>
                                    <entry>Determines what happens when the thread pool (and queue, if enabled) is
                                    full. The default is to run on the caller's thread. "Abort" throws an runtime
                                    exception. "Discard" discards the message, "DiscardOldest" discards the
                                    oldest entry in the queue. Note that these values might change, for example a
                                    "Wait" value might get added in the future.</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>thread_naming_pattern</entry>
                                    <entry>Determines how threads are named that are running from thread pools in 
                                    concurrent stack. Valid values include any combination of "cl" letters, where
                                    "c" includes the cluster name and "l" includes local address of the channel.
                                        The default is "cl"
                                    </entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </table>
                </para>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Elimination of up and down threads</title>

            <para>
                By removing the 2 queues/protocol and the associated 2 threads, we effectively reduce the number of
                threads needed to handle a message, and thus context switching overhead. We also get clear and unambiguous
                semantics for Channel.send(): now, all messages are sent down the stack on the caller's thread and
                the send() call only returns once the message has been put on the network. In addition, an exception will
                only be propagated back to the caller if the message has not yet been placed in a retransmit buffer.
                Otherwise, JGroups simply logs the error message but keeps retransmitting the message. Therefore,
                if the caller gets an exception, the message should be re-sent.
            </para>
            <para>
                On the receiving side, a message is handled by a thread pool, either the regular or OOB thread pool. Both
                thread pools can be completely eliminated, so that we can save even more threads and thus further
                reduce context switching. The point is that the developer is now able to control the threading behavior
                almost completely.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Concurrent message delivery</title>
            <para>
                Up to version 2.5, all messages received were processed by a single thread, even if the messages were
                sent by different senders. For instance, if sender A sent messages 1,2 and 3, and B sent message 34 and 45,
                and if A's messages were all received first, then B's messages 34 and 35 could only be processed after
                messages 1-3 from A were processed !
            </para>
            <para>
                Now, we can process messages from different senders in parallel, e.g. messages 1, 2 and 3 from A can be
                processed by one thread from the thread pool and messages 34 and 35 from B can be processed on a different
                thread.
            </para>
            <para>
                As a result, we get a speedup of almost N for a cluster of N if every node is sending messages and we
                configure the thread pool to have at least N threads. There is actually a unit test
                (ConcurrentStackTest.java) which demonstrates this.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Out-of-band messages</title>
            <para>
                OOB messages completely ignore any ordering constraints the stack might have. Any message marked as OOB
                will be processed by the OOB thread pool. This is necessary in cases where we don't want the message
                processing to wait until all other messages from the same sender have been processed, e.g. in the
                heartbeat case: if sender P sends 5 messages and then a response to a heartbeat request received from
                some other node, then the time taken to process P's 5 messages might take longer than the heartbeat
                timeout, so that P might get falsely suspected ! However, if the heartbeat response is marked as OOB,
                then it will get processed by the OOB thread pool and therefore might be concurrent to its previously
                sent 5 messages and not trigger a false suspicion.
            </para>
            <para>
                The 2 unit tests UNICAST_OOB_Test and NAKACK_OOB_Test demonstrate how OOB messages influence the ordering,
                for both unicast and multicast messages.
            </para>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>Replacing the default and OOB thread pools</title>
            <para>
                In 2.7, there are 3 thread pools and 4 thread factories in TP:
                <table>
                    <title>Thread pools and factories in TP</title>

                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <colspec align="left" />

                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center">Name</entry>
                                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Default thread pool</entry>
                                <entry>This is the pools for handling incoming messages. It can be fetched using
                                    getDefaultThreadPool() and replaced using setDefaultThreadPool(). When setting a
                                    thread pool, the old thread pool (if any) will be shutdown and all of it tasks
                                    cancelled first
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>OOB thread pool</entry>
                                <entry>This is the pool for handling incoming OOB messages. Methods to get and set
                                    it are getOOBThreadPool() and setOOBThreadPool()</entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry>Timer thread pool</entry>
                                <entry>This is the thread pool for the timer. The max number of threads is set through
                                the timer.num_threads property. The timer thread pool cannot be set, it can only
                                be retrieved using getTimer(). However, the thread factory of the timer
                                can be replaced (see below)</entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry>Default thread factory</entry>
                                <entry>This is the thread factory (org.jgroups.util.ThreadFactory) of the default
                                    thread pool, which handles incoming messages. A thread pool factory is used to
                                    name threads and possibly make them daemons.
                                    It can be accessed using
                                    getDefaultThreadPoolThreadFactory() and setDefaultThreadPoolThreadFactory()</entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry>OOB thread factory</entry>
                                <entry>This is the thread factory for the OOB thread pool. It can be retrieved
                                using getOOBThreadPoolThreadFactory() and set using method
                                setOOBThreadPoolThreadFactory()</entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry>Timer thread factory</entry>
                                <entry>This is the thread factory for the timer thread pool. It can be accessed
                                using getTimerThreadFactory() and setTimerThreadFactory()</entry>
                            </row>

                            <row>
                                <entry>Global thread factory</entry>
                                <entry>The global thread factory can get used (e.g. by protocols) to create threads
                                which don't live in the transport, e.g. the FD_SOCK server socket handler thread.
                                Each protocol has a method getTransport(). Once the TP is obtained, getThreadFactory()
                                can be called to get the global thread factory. The global thread factory
                                can be replaced with setThreadFactory()</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </table>

            </para>
        </section>


        <section>
            <title>Sharing of thread pools between channels in the same JVM</title>
            <para>
                In 2.7, the default and OOB thread pools can be shared between instances running inside the same JVM. The
                advantage here is that multiple channels running within the same JVM can pool (and therefore save) threads.
                The disadvantage is that thread naming will not show to which channel instance an incoming thread
                belongs to.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that we can not just shared thread pools between JChannels within the same JVM, but we can also
                share entire transports. For details see <xref linkend="SharedTransport">this section</xref>.
            </para>
        </section>



    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Misc</title>
        <section>
            <title>Shunning</title>
            Let's say we have 4 members in a group: {A,B,C,D}. When a member (say D) is expelled from the group, e.g.
            because it didn't respond to are-you-alive messages, and later comes back, then it is shunned. Shunning
            causes a member to leave the group and re-join, if this is enabled on the Channel. To enable automatic
            re-connects, the AUTO_RECONNECT option has to be set on the Channel:
            <screen>
                channel.setOpt(Channel.AUTO_RECONNECT, Boolean.TRUE);
            </screen>

            
            <para>To enable shunning, set FD.shun and GMS.shun to true.</para>

            Let's look at a more detailed example. Say member D is overloaded, and doesn't respond to are-you-alive
            messages (done by the failure detection (FD) protocol). It is therefore suspected and excluded. The new
            view for A, B and C will be {A,B,C}, however for D the view is still {A,B,C,D}. So when D comes back and
            sends messages to the group, or any individiual member, those messages will be discarded, because A,B and
            C don't see D in their view. D is shunned when A,B or C receive an are-you-alive message from D, or D
            shuns itself when it receives a view which doesn't include D.<para/>

            So shunning is always a unilateral decision. However, things may be different if all members exclude each
            other from the group. For example, say we have a switch connecting A, B, C and D. If someone pulls all
            plugs on the switch, or powers the switch down, then A, B, C and D will all form singleton groups, that is,
            each member thinks it's the only member in the group. When the switch goes back to normal, then each member
            will shun everybody else (a real shun fest :-)). This is clearly not desirable, so in this case shunning
            should be turned off:
            <screen>
            &lt;FD timeout="2000" max_tries="3" shun="false"/&gt; ... &lt;pbcast.GMS join_timeout="3000" shun="false"/&gt;
            </screen>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Handling network partitions</title>

        <para>
            Network partitions can be caused by switch, router or network interface crashes, among other things. If we
            have a cluster {A,B,C,D,E} spread across 2 subnets {A,B,C} and {D,E} and the switch to which D and E are
            connected crashes, then we end up with a network partition, with subclusters {A,B,C} and {D,E}.
        </para>
        <para>
            A, B and C can ping each other, but not D or E, and vice versa. We now have 2 coordinators, A and D. Both
            subclusters operate independently, for example, if we maintain a shared state, subcluster {A,B,C} replicate
            changes to A, B and C.
        </para>
        <para>
            This means, that if during the partition, some clients access {A,B,C}, and others {D,E}, then we end up
            with different states in both subclusters. When a partition heals, the merge protocol (e.g. MERGE2) will
            notify A and D that there were 2 subclusters and merge them back into {A,B,C,D,E}, with A being the new
            coordinator and D ceasing to be coordinator.
        </para>
        <para>
            The question is what happens with the 2 diverged substates ?
        </para>
        <para>
            There are 2 solutions to merging substates: first we can attempt to create a new state from the 2 substates,
            and secondly we can shut down all members of the <emphasis>non primary partition</emphasis>, such that they
            have to re-join and possibly reacquire the state from a member in the primary partition.
        </para>
        <para>
            In both cases, the application has to handle a MergeView (subclass of View), as shown in the code below:
            <screen>
                public void viewAccepted(View view) {
                    if(view instanceof MergeView) {
                        MergeView tmp=(MergeView)view;
                        Vector&lt;View&gt; subgroups=tmp.getSubgroups();
                        // merge state or determine primary partition
                        // run this in a separate thread !
                    }
                }
            </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            It is essential that the merge view handling code run on a separate thread if it needs more than a few
            milliseconds, or else it would block the calling thread.
        </para>
        <para>
            The MergeView contains a list of views, each view represents a subgroups and has the list of members which
            formed this group.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Merging substates</title>
            <para>
                The application has to merge the substates from the various subgroups ({A,B,C} and {D,E}) back into one
                single state for {A,B,C,D,E}. This task <emphasis>has</emphasis> to be done by the application because
                JGroups knows nothing about the application state, other than it is a byte buffer.
            </para>
            <para>
                If the in-memory state is backed by a database, then the solution is easy: simply discard the in-memory
                state and fetch it (eagerly or lazily) from the DB again. This of course assumes that the members of
                the 2 subgroups were able to write their changes to the DB. However, this is often not the case, as
                connectivity to the DB might have been severed by the network partition.
            </para>
            <para>
                Another solution could involve tagging the state with time stamps. On merging, we could compare the
                time stamps for the substates and let the substate with the more recent time stamps win.
            </para>
            <para>
                Yet another solution could increase a counter for a state each time the state has been modified. The state
                with the highest counter wins.
            </para>
            <para>
                Again, the merging of state can only be done by the application. Whatever algorithm is picked to merge
                state, it has to be deterministic.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>The primary partition approach</title>
        </section>
        <para>
            The primary partition approach is simple: on merging, one subgroup is designated as the
            <emphasis>primary partition</emphasis> and all others as non-primary partitions. The members in the primary
            partition don't do anything, whereas the members in the non-primary partitions need to drop their state and
            re-initialize their state from fresh state obtained from a member of the primary partition.
        </para>
        <para>
            The code to find the primary partition needs to be deterministic, so that all members pick the <emphasis>
            same</emphasis> primary partition. This could be for example the first view in the MergeView, or we could
            sort all members of the new MergeView and pick the subgroup which contained the new coordinator (the one
            from the consolidated MergeView). Another possible solution could be to pick the largest subgroup, and, if
            there is a tie, sort the tied views lexicographically (all Addresses have a compareTo() method) and pick the
            subgroup with the lowest ranked member.
        </para>
        <para>
            Here's code which picks as primary partition the first view in the MergeView, then re-acquires the state from
            the <emphasis>new</emphasis> coordinator of the combined view:
            <screen>
                public static void main(String[] args) throws Exception {
                       final JChannel ch=new JChannel("/home/bela/udp.xml");
                       ch.setReceiver(new ExtendedReceiverAdapter() {
                           public void viewAccepted(View new_view) {
                               handleView(ch, new_view);
                           }
                       });
                       ch.connect("x");
                       while(ch.isConnected())
                           Util.sleep(5000);
                   }

                private static void handleView(JChannel ch, View new_view) {
                    if(new_view instanceof MergeView) {
                        ViewHandler handler=new ViewHandler(ch, (MergeView)new_view);
                        handler.start(); // requires separate thread as we don't want to block JGroups
                    }
                }

                private static class ViewHandler extends Thread {
                    JChannel ch;
                    MergeView view;

                    private ViewHandler(JChannel ch, MergeView view) {
                        this.ch=ch;
                        this.view=view;
                    }

                    public void run() {
                        Vector&lt;View&gt; subgroups=view.getSubgroups();
                        View tmp_view=subgroups.firstElement(); // picks the first
                        Address local_addr=ch.getLocalAddress();
                        if(!tmp_view.getMembers().contains(local_addr)) {
                            System.out.println("I (" + local_addr + ") am not member of the new primary partition (" + tmp_view +
                                    "), will re-acquire the state");
                            try {
                                ch.getState(null, 30000);
                            }
                            catch(Exception ex) {
                            }
                        }
                        else {
                            System.out.println("I (" + local_addr + ") am member of the new primary partition (" + tmp_view +
                                    "), will do nothing");
                        }
                    }
                }
            </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            The handleView() method is called from viewAccepted(), which is called whenever there is a new view. It spawns
            a new thread which gets the subgroups from the MergeView, and picks the first subgroup to be the primary
            partition. Then, if it was a member of the primary partition, it does nothing, and if not, it reaqcuires
            the state from the coordinator of the primary partition (A).
        </para>
        <para>
            The downside to the primary partition approach is that work (= state changes) on the non-primary partition
            is discarded on merging. However, that's only problematic if the data was purely in-memory data, and not
            backed by persistent storage. If the latter's the case, use state merging discussed above.
        </para>
        <para>
            It would be simpler to shut down the non-primary partition as soon as the network partition is detected, but
            that a non trivial problem, as we don't know whether {D,E} simply crashed, or whether they're still alive,
            but were partitioned away by the crash of a switch. This is called a <emphasis>split brain syndrome</emphasis>,
            and means that none of the members has enough information to determine whether it is in the primary or
            non-primary partition, by simply exchanging messages.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>The Split Brain syndrome and primary partitions</title>
            <para>
                In certain situations, we can avoid having multiple subgroups where every subgroup is able to make
                progress, and on merging having to discard state of the non-primary partitions.
            </para>
            <para>
                If we have a fixed membership, e.g. the cluster always consists of 5 nodes, then we can run code on
                a view reception that determines the primary partition. This code
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>assumes that the primary partition has to have at least 3 nodes</listitem>
                    <listitem>any cluster which has less than 3 nodes doesn't accept modfications. This could be done for
                        shared state for example, by simply making the {D,E} partition read-only. Clients can access the
                        {D,E} partition and read state, but not modify it.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        As an alternative, clusters without at least 3 members could shut down, so in this case D and
                        E would leave the cluster.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                The algorithm is shown in pseudo code below:
                <screen>
                    On initialization:
                        - Mark the node as read-only
                    
                    On view change V:
                        - If V has >= N members:
                            - If not read-write: get state from coordinator and switch to read-write
                        - Else: switch to read-only
                </screen>
            </para>
            <para>
                Of course, the above mechanism requires that at least 3 nodes are up at any given time, so upgrades have
                to be done in a staggered way, taking only one node down at a time. In the worst case, however, this
                mechanism leaves the cluster read-only and notifies a system admin, who can fix the issue. This is still
                better than shutting the entire cluster down. 
            </para>
        </section>

    </section>


    <section>
        <title>Flushing: making sure every node in the cluster received a message</title>

        When sending messages, the properties of the default stacks (udp.xml, tcp.xml) are that all messages are delivered
        reliably to all (non-crashed) members. However, there are no guarantees with respect to the view in which a message
        will get delivered. For example, when a member A with view V1={A,B,C} multicasts message M1 to the group and D joins
        at about the same time, then D may or may not receive M1, and there is no guarantee that A, B and C receive M1 in
        V1 or V2={A,B,C,D}.

        <para>
            To change this, we can turn on virtual synchrony (by adding FLUSH to the top of the stack), which guarantees that
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    A message M sent in V1 will be delivered in V1. So, in the example above, M1 would get delivered in
                    view V1; by A, B and C, but not by D.
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    The set of messages seen by members in V1 is the same for all members before a new view V2 is installed.
                    This is important, as it ensures that all members in a given view see the same messages. For example,
                    in a group {A,B,C}, C sends 5 messages. A receives all 5 messages, but B doesn't. Now C crashes before
                    it can retransmit the messages to B. FLUSH will now ensure, that before installing V2={A,B} (excluding
                    C), B gets C's 5 messages. This is done through the flush protocol, which has all members reconcile
                    their messages before a new view is installed. In this case, A will send C's 5 messages to B.
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            Sometimes it is important to know that every node in the cluster received all messages up to a certain point,
            even if there is no new view being installed. To do this (initiate a manual flush), an application programmer
            can call Channel.startFlush() to start a flush and Channel.stopFlush() to terminate it.
        </para>

        <para>
            Channel.startFlush() flushes all pending messages out of the system. This stops all senders (calling
            Channel.down() during a flush will block until the flush has completed)<footnote><para>Note that block()
            will be called in a Receiver when the flush is about to start and unblock() will be called when it ends</para></footnote>.
            When startFlush() returns, the caller knows that (a) no messages will get sent anymore until stopFlush() is
            called and (b) all members have received all messages sent before startFlush() was called.
        </para>

        <para>
            Channel.stopFlush() terminates the flush protocol, no blocked senders can resume sending messages.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note that the FLUSH protocol has to be present on top of the stack, or else the flush will fail.
        </para>
        
    </section>
</chapter>