<chapter>
    <title>Installation and Configuration</title>

    <para>The installation refers to version 2.5 of JGroups. Refer to the installation
        instructions that are shipped with JGroups for details.</para>

    <para>Note that these instructions are also available in the
        JGroups distribution (<filename>INSTALL.HTML</filename>).
    </para>

    <para>JGroups comes in a binary and a source version: the binary
        version is <filename>JGroups-2.x.x.bin.zip</filename>, the source
        version is <filename>JGroups-2.x.x.src.zip</filename>. The binary
        version contains the JGroups JAR file, plus a number of JARs needed
        by JGroups. The source version contains all source files, plus
        several JAR files needed by JGroups, e.g. ANT to build JGroups from
        source.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Requirements</title>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>JGroups 2.5 requires JDK 5 or higher.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>There is no JNI code present so it should run on all platforms.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you want to generate HTML-based test reports from the
                    unittests, then xalan.jar needs to be in the CLASSPATH (also
                    available in the lib directory)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Installing the binary distribution</title>

        <para>The binary version contains</para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>jgroups-all.jar: the JGroups library including the
                    demos</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>CREDITS: list of contributors</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>INSTALL.html: this file</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>log4j.jar. This JAR is optional, for example if JDK logging is used, we don't need it.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>Place the JAR files somewhere in your <envar>CLASSPATH</envar>, and you're ready to start using
            JGroups. If you want to use the JGroups JMS protocol (<classname>org.jgroups.protocols.JMS</classname>),
            then you will also need to place jms.jar somewhere in your CLASSPATH.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Installing the source distribution</title>

        <para>The source version consists of the following directories and files:</para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>src: the sources</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>test: unit and stress tests</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>conf: configuration files needed by JGroups, plus default protocol stack definitions</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>doc: documentation</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>lib: various JARs needed to build and run
                    JGroups:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/">Ant
                            </ulink>
                            JARs: used to build JGroups. If you already have
                            Ant installed, you won't need these files
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>jms.jar: JMS library. Needed only if you intend to
                            run the org.jgroups.protocols.JMS protocol</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>junit.jar: to run the
                            <ulink url="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</ulink> test cases
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/">xalan.jar</ulink>: to format the output of
                            the JUnit tests using an XSLT converter to HTML
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>log4j.jar</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>etc</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Building JGroups (source distribution only)</title>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Unzip the source distribution, e.g. unzip
                    JGroups-2.x.x.src.zip. This will create the JGroups-2.x.x
                    directory (root directory) under the current directory.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>cd to the root directory</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Modify build.properties if you want to use a Java
                    compiler other than javac (e.g. jikes), or if you want to change the
                interface JGroups uses for sending and receiving messages</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>On UNIX systems use <filename>build.sh</filename>, on Windows
                    <filename>build.bat</filename>:
                    <userinput>$&gt;
                        ./build.sh compile</userinput>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>This will compile all Java files (into the <filename>classes</filename> directory).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To generate the JARs:
                    <userinput>$&gt; ./build.sh
                        jar</userinput>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>This will generate the following JAR files in the
                    <filename>dist</filename>  directory:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <filename>jgroups-core.jar</filename>
                            - the core JGroups libraries
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <filename>jgroups-all.jar</filename>
                            - the complete JGroups libraries including demos and unit tests
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The
                    <filename>CLASSPATH</filename>
                    now has to be set accordingly: the following directories and/or JARs have to be included:
                </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <filename>&lt;JGroups
                                rootdir&gt;/classes</filename>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <filename>&lt;JGroups
                                rootdir&gt;/conf</filename>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All needed JAR files in
                            <filename>&lt;JGroups
                                rootdir&gt;/lib</filename>
                            . To build from sources, the two
                            Ant JARs are required. To run unit tests, the JUnit (and
                            possibly Xalan) JARs are needed.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To generate JavaDocs simple run
                    <userinput>$&gt;
                        ./build.sh javadoc</userinput>
                    and the Javadoc documentation will
                    be generated in the
                    <filename>dist/javadoc</filename>
                    directory
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Note that - if you already have Ant installed on your
                    system - you do not need to use build.sh or build.bat, simply
                    invoke ant on the build.xml file. To be able to invoked ant
                    from any directory below the root directory, place
                    <userinput>ANT_ARGS="-find build.xml -emacs"</userinput>
                    into
                    the
                    <filename>.antrc</filename>
                    file in your home
                    directory.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>For more details on Ant see
                    <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/"/>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Testing your Setup</title>

        <para>To see whether your system can find the JGroups classes,
            execute the following command:</para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.Version
        </screen>

        <para>or (from JGroups 2.2.8 on)</para>

        <screen>
            java -jar jgroups-all.jar
        </screen>

        <para>You should see the following output (more or less) if the
            class is found:</para>

        <screen>
            bela@dell /cygdrive/c/JGroups/dist
            $ java -jar jgroups-all.jar

            Version:        2.6.0 pre-alpha
            CVS:            $Id: installation.xml,v 1.6 2009/05/13 13:22:08 belaban Exp $
        </screen>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Running a Demo Program</title>

        <para>To test whether JGroups works okay on your machine, run
            the following command twice:</para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.demos.Draw
        </screen>

        <para>2 whiteboard windows should appear as shown in <xref linkend="DrawScreenshotFig"/>.

            <figure id="DrawScreenshotFig"><title>Screenshot of 2 Draw instances</title>
                <graphic fileref="images/DrawScreenshot.png" format="PNG" align="center"  />
            </figure>

            Both windows should show 2 in their title bars. This means that the two instances found each other
            and formed a group.</para>

        <para>When drawing in one window, the second instance should also
            be updated. As the default group transport uses IP multicast, make
            sure that - if you want start the 2 instances in different subnets
            - IP multicast is enabled. If this is not the case, the 2
            instances won't find each other and the sample won't work.</para>

        <para>You can change the properties of the demo to for example use
            a different transport if multicast doesn't work (it should always
            work on the same machine). Please consult the documentation to see how to do this.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Using IP Multicasting without a network connection</title>

        <para>Sometimes there isn't a network connection (e.g. DSL modem
            is down), or we want to multicast only on the local machine. For
            this the loopback interface (typically lo) can be configured,
            e.g.</para>

        <screen>
            route add -net 224.0.0.0 netmask 240.0.0.0 dev lo
        </screen>

        <para>This means that all traffic directed to the 224.0.0.0
            network will be sent to the loopback interface, which means it
            doesn't need any network to be running. Note that the 224.0.0.0
            network is a placeholder for all multicast addresses in most UNIX
            implementations: it will catch
            <emphasis>all</emphasis> multicast
            traffic. This is an undocumented feature of
            <filename>/sbin/route</filename>
            and may not work across all UNIX
            flavors. The above instructions may also work for Windows systems,
            but this hasn't been tested. Note that not all systems allow
            multicast traffic to use the loopback interface.
        </para>

        <para>Typical home networks have a gateway/firewall with 2 NICs:
            the first (eth0) is connected to the outside world (Internet
            Service Provider), the second (eth1) to the internal network, with
            the gateway firewalling/masquerading traffic between the internal
            and external networks. If no route for multicast traffic is added,
            the default will be to use the fdefault gateway, which will
            typically direct the multicast traffic towards the ISP. To prevent
            this (e.g. ISP drops multicast traffic, or latency is too high),
            we recommend to add a route for multicast traffic which goes to
            the internal network (e.g. eth1).</para>

    </section>

    <section id="ItDoesntWork">
        <title>It doesn't work !</title>

        <para>Make sure your machine is set up correctly for IP
            multicast. There are 2 test programs that can be used to detect
            this: McastReceiverTest and McastSenderTest. Start
            McastReceiverTest, e.g.</para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.tests.McastReceiverTest -mcast_addr 224.10.10.10 -port 5555
        </screen>

        <para>Then start McastSenderTest:</para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.tests.McastSenderTest -mcast_addr 224.10.10.10 -port 5555
        </screen>

        <para>If you want to bind to a specific network interface card (NIC), use -bind_addr 192.168.0.2,
        where 192.168.0.2 is the IP address of the NIC to which you want to bind. Use this parameter in both
        sender and receiver.</para>

        <para>You should be able to type in the McastSenderTest window and
            see the output in the McastReceiverTest. If not, try to use -ttl
            32 in the sender. If this still fails, consult a system
            administrator to help you setup IP multicast correctly. If you are
            the system administrator, look for another job :-)</para>

        <para>Other means of getting help: there is a public forum on
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.com/jira/browse/JGRP">JIRA</ulink>
            for questions. Also consider subscribing to the javagroups-users
            mailing list to discuss such and other problems.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>The instances still don't find each other !</title>

        <para>In this case we have to use a sledgehammer (running only
            under JDK 1.4. and higher): we can enable the above sender and
            receiver test to use all available interfaces for sending and
            receiving. One of them will certainly be the right one... Start
            the receiver as follows:</para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.tests.McastReceiverTest1_4 -mcast_addr 228.8.8.8 -use_all_interfaces
        </screen>

        <para>The multicast receiver uses the 1.4 functionality to list
            <emphasis>all available network interfaces and bind to all of
                them</emphasis>
            (including the loopback interface). This means
            that whichever interface a packet comes in on, we will receive it.
            Now start the sender:
        </para>

        <screen>
            java org.jgroups.tests.McastSenderTest1_4 -mcast_addr 228.8.8.8 -use_all_interfaces
        </screen>

        <para>The sender will also determine the available network
            interfaces and send each packet over all interfaces.</para>

        <para>This test can be used to find out which network interface to
            bind to when previously no packets were received. E.g. when you
            see the following output in the receiver:</para>

        <screen>
            bash-2.03$ java org.jgroups.tests.McastReceiverTest1_4 -mcast_addr 228.8.8.8 -bind_addr 192.168.168.4
            Socket=0.0.0.0/0.0.0.0:5555, bind interface=/192.168.168.4
            dd [sender=192.168.168.4:5555]
            dd [sender=192.168.168.1:5555]
            dd [sender=192.168.168.2:5555]
        </screen>

        <para>you know that you can bind to any of the 192.168.168.{1,2,4}
            interfaces to receive your multicast packets. In this case you
            would need to modify your protocol spec to include
            bind_addr=192.168.168.2 in UDP, e.g.
            <parameter>"UDP(mcast_addr=228.8.8.8;bind_addr=192.168.168.2):..."
            </parameter>
            .
        </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Problems with IPv6</title>

        <para>Another source of problems might be the use of IPv6, and/or misconfiguration of
            <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. If you
            communicate between an IPv4 and an IPv6 host, and they are not
            able to find each other, try the
            <parameter>java.net.preferIP4Stack=true</parameter>
            property,
            e.g.
        </para>

        <screen>
            java -Djava.net.preferIPv4Stack=true org.jgroups.demos.Draw -props file:/home/bela/udp.xml
        </screen>

        <para>JDK 1.4.1 uses IPv6 by default, although is has a dual stack, that is, it also supports IPv4.
            <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4/docs/guide/net/ipv6_guide/">Here's</ulink>
            more details on the subject.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Wiki</title>
        <para>
            There is a wiki which lists FAQs and their solutions at
            <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=JGroups"/>. It is frequently updated and a useful companion
            to this user's guide.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>I have discovered a bug !</title>

        <para>If you think that you discovered a bug, submit a bug report
            on
            <ulink
                    url="http://jira.jboss.com/jira/browse/JGRP">JIRA</ulink>
            or send
            email to javagroups-developers if you're unsure about it. Please
            include the following information:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Version of JGroups (java org.jgroups.Version)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Platform (e.g. Solaris 8)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Version of JDK (e.g. JDK 1.4.2_07)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stack trace. Use kill -3 PID on UNIX systems or
                    CTRL-BREAK on windows machines</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Small program that reproduces the bug</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </section>

</chapter>
