<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
        "../../../../docbook-support/support/docbook-dtd/docbookx.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY overview     SYSTEM "modules/overview.xml">
        <!ENTITY blocks       SYSTEM "modules/blocks.xml">
        <!ENTITY protocols    SYSTEM "modules/protocols.xml.tmp">
        <!ENTITY installation SYSTEM "modules/installation.xml">
        <!ENTITY api          SYSTEM "modules/api.xml">
        <!ENTITY advanced     SYSTEM "modules/advanced.xml">
        <!ENTITY writing      SYSTEM "modules/writing.xml">
        ]>

<book>

    <bookinfo>
        <title>Reliable Multicasting with the JGroups Toolkit</title>
        <pubdate>$Date: 2009/01/23 09:50:35 $</pubdate>
        <releaseinfo>$Revision: 1.12 $</releaseinfo>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Bela</firstname>
                <surname>Ban</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>
                        <ulink url="http://www.jgroups.org/">JGroups Project</ulink>
                    </orgname>
                    <address>
                        <email>belaban@yahoo.com</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>1998-2008</year>
            <holder>Bela Ban</holder>
        </copyright>
         <copyright>
            <year>2006-2008</year>
            <holder>Red Hat Inc</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice>
            <para>This document is copyrighted. Copies are allowed for
                personal use. Redistribution only with written permission of the author(s).</para>
        </legalnotice>
    </bookinfo>

    <preface>
        <title>Foreword</title>

        <para>This is the Programmer's and User's Guide for
            JGroups. It provides information about the following areas:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Installation and configuration.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Using JGroups.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Architecture and implementation of JGroups. Focus on the
                        protocol stack and protocols.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>Most of the Installation and User's Guide has been copied
            from what is freely available on the
            <ulink
                    url="http://www.jgroups.org/">JGroups web site</ulink>
            .
            However, the focus of this document is to introduce programmers
            who want to learn more about JGroups to the architecture and
            implementation of JGroups. I will for example go into the
            details of the protocol stack, how a message traverses the stack,
            and how protocols can process it. I will also explain the various
            design decisions I had to make when designing JGroups, which
            hopefully leads to a better understanding of why things are the
            way they are.
        </para>

        <para>Here are a couple of points I want to abide by throughout
            this book:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>I like brevity. I will strive to describe concepts as
                        clearly as possible (for a non-native English speaker) and will
                        refrain from saying more than I have to to make a point.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>I like simplicity. Keep It Simple and Stupid. This is
                        one of the biggest goals I have both in writing this book
                        and in writing JGroups. It is easy to explain simple
                        concepts in complex terms, but it is hard to explain a
                        complex system in simple terms. I'll try to do the
                        latter.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>


        <bridgehead>So, how did it all start?</bridgehead>

        <para>I spent 1998-1999 at the Computer Science Department at
            Cornell University for a post-doc, in Ken Birman's group. Ken is
            credited with inventing the group communication paradigm,
            especially the Virtual Synchrony model. At the time they were
            working on their third generation group communication prototype,
            called Ensemble. Ensemble followed Horus (written in C by Robbert
            VanRenesse), which followed ISIS (written by Ken Birman, also in
            C). Ensemble was written in OCaml, developed at INRIA, which is a
            functional language and related to ML. I never liked the OCaml
            language, which in my opinion has a hideous syntax. Therefore I
            never got warm with Ensemble either.</para>

        <para>However, Ensemble had a Java interface (implemented by a
            student in a semester project) which allowed me to program in Java
            and use Ensemble underneath. The Java part would require that an
            Ensemble process was running somewhere on the same machine, or
            within the same network, and would connect to it via a
            bidirectional pipe. The student had developed a simple protocol
            for talking to the Ensemble engine, and extended the engine as
            well to talk back to Java.</para>

        <para>However, I still needed to compile and install the Ensemble
            runtime for each different platform, which is exactly why Java was
            developed in the first place: portability.</para>

        <para>Therefore I started writing a simple framework (now
            <classname>JChannel</classname>
            ), which would allow me to treat
            Ensemble as just another group communication transport, which
            could be replaced at any time by a pure Java solution. And soon I
            found myself working on a pure Java implementation of the group
            communication transport (now:
            <classname>ProtocolStack</classname>
            ). I figured that a pure Java
            implementation would have a much bigger impact that something
            written in Ensemble. In the end I didn't spend much time writing
            scientific papers that nobody would read anyway (I guess I'm not a
            good scientist, at least not a theoretical one), but rather code
            for JGroups, which could have a much bigger impact. For me,
            knowing that real-life projects/products are using JGroups is
            much more satisfactory than having a paper accepted at a
            conference/journal.
        </para>

        <para>That's why, after my time was up, I left Cornell and
            academia altogether, and started a job in the industry: with
            Fujitsu Network Communications in Silicon Valley.</para>

        <para>At around that time (May 2000), SourceForge had just opened
            its site, and I decided to use it for hosting JGroups. I guess
            this was a major boost for JGroups because now other developers
            could work on the code. From then on, the page hit and download
            numbers for JGroups have steadily risen.</para>

        <para>
            In the fall of 2002, Sacha Labourey contacted me, letting me know that JGroups was being used by JBoss for
            their clustering implementation. I joined JBoss in 2003 and have been working on JGroups and JBossCache. My
            goal is to make JGroups the most widely used clustering software in the Java space...
        </para>

        <para>Bela Ban, San Jose, Aug 2002, Kreuzlingen Switzerland 2006</para>

    </preface>

    <preface>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>

        <para>I want to thank all contributors to JGroups, present and
            past, for their work. Without you, this project would never have
            taken off the ground.</para>

        <para>I also want to thank Ken Birman and Robbert VanRenesse for
            many fruitful discussions of all aspects of group communication in
            particular and distributed systems in general.</para>

        <para>I want to dedicate this book to Jeannette and Michelle.</para>

    </preface>

    &overview;
    &installation;
    &api;
    &blocks;
    &advanced;
    &writing;
    &protocols;


    <bibliography>

        <bibliomixed id="Ensemble:1997">
            <title>The Ensemble Distributed Communication System</title>
            ,
            <orgname>CS Dept Cornell University</orgname>
            ,
            <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
            .
            <releaseinfo>
                <ulink
                        url="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/Info/Projects/Ensemble/index.html"/>
            </releaseinfo>
            .
        </bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="Gamma:1995">
            <firstname>Erich</firstname>
            <surname>Gamma</surname>
            ,
            <firstname>Richard</firstname>
            <surname>Helm</surname>
            ,
            <firstname>Ralph</firstname>
            <surname>Johnson</surname>
            , and
            <firstname>John</firstname>
            <surname>Vlissides</surname>
            .
            <title>Design Patterns: Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented
                Software</title>
            .
            <publishername>Addison-Wesley</publishername>
            ,
            <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
            .
        </bibliomixed>

    </bibliography>

</book>

